# Jessica Schroeder, Ph.D.

jesscs@cs.washington.edu

https://jesscs.github.io/

### **SUMMARY**

Research scientist specialized in human-computer interaction (HCI) and health informatics, with extensive experience in conducting *formative studies* to identify needs and opportunities; *iterative design and development* of novel methods and tools to support those needs; and *evaluations* to examine usage and develop design implications for future tools.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### 2020-Present Research Scientist, Evidation Health

Collaboratively designs and conducts novel studies to address internal and client research questions investigating a wide range of health-related perspectives, behaviors, and backgrounds.

### 2014 - 2020 Research Assistant, University of Washington

Investigated supporting people and their health providers in collecting, analyzing, and interpreting patient-generated data to meet personalized health goals in multiple health contexts.

Conducted surveys and interviews to characterize needs and opportunities in health contexts.

Collaborated with health providers in the design and evaluation of novel prototype health apps, including mobile apps and interactive, exploratory visualizations.

Research resulted in related grants from the NSF (\$500k) and the NIH (\$1.5M).

More detailed descriptions available on my personal website.

# Summer 2017 Research Intern, Microsoft Research

Conducted a feasibility study to investigate how a mobile app can support behavioral therapy.

Designed and analyzed surveys to: 1) characterize significant positive changes in anxiety, depression, and coping skill use; 2) develop a theoretical model to describe how the app supported these improvements; and 3) distill design implications for future tools.

Identified opportunities for machine learning techniques to provide personalized and context-aware suggestions to help people identify feasible and useful positive coping skills.

### 2013 - 2014 Project Manager, Harvey Mudd Clinic

Led development of a web app to provide personalized vacation recommendations for Expedia.

### 2013 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Carnegie Mellon HCII

Investigated augmentations of a chronic illness forum to help people find credible information.

# 2012 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Pomona College

Developed a web app to identify fusion genes, which have implications in cancer.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### 2014 - Present University of Washington, Seattle, WA

PhD, Computer Science & Engineering. GPA: 3.9

M.S. earned 12/2016

Dissertation: Goal-Directed Self-Tracking in the Management of Chronic Health Conditions

Advisors: James Fogarty, Sean Munson

### 2010 - 2014 Pomona College, Claremont, CA

B.A., Computer Science. GPA: 3.9

# **AWARDS & HONORS**

2017, 2018	Best Paper Award (CHI 2017) and Honorable Mentions (CHI 2017, DIS 2018)
2016	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Awardee
2014	Marilyn Fries Endowed Regental Fellowship Recipient
2014	ARCS Foundation Fellow
2014	Harvey Mudd Computer Science Clinic Team Award Winner
2013	DREU-CRAW Participant
2013	Grace Hopper Scholarship Recipient

2010 - 2013 Pomona College Scholar

#### **SKILLS**

User Research Semi-structured interviews, surveys, field studies, observation, contextual inquiry.

Data Analysis Qualitative data analysis (e.g., coding, thematic analysis, affinity diagraming);

Quantitative data analysis (e.g., R, Python, Pandas, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn).

Prototyping Prototypes, mobile and web app development (e.g., Angular, Ionic, D3.js).

Communication/Leadership Project management, scientific & technical writing, presentations.

### TEACHING, SERVICE, AND LEADERSHIP

Reviewer CHI 2017-2020; CSCW 2018-2019; DIS 2018-2019; IMWUT 2019.

Teaching Assistant Designed and graded assignments, critiqued projects, and advised UW graduate students

in CSE 510: Advanced Topics in HCI (Winter 2018, Fall 2018).

HCI Seminar Lead Led improvements to the Computer Science department's weekly HCI seminar and

organized quarterly themes, presentations, and feedback (January 2017—June 2018).

UW CSE Graduate
Admissions Volunteer
Coordinated one-on-ones with faculty and current graduate students and organized social activity (Winter 2018); reviewed graduate student applications (Fall 2016).

Orientation Leader
Coordinated one-on-ones with faculty and current graduate students and organized social activity (Winter 2018); reviewed graduate student applications (Fall 2016).

Organized orientation for the new Computer Science graduate students (Fall 2016).

Worked with Pomona students to improve their writing (Fall 2011—Spring 2014).

Senior Science Fellow for the 2013/2014 academic year.

#### **SELECT PUBLICATIONS**

Full publication lists available on my personal website and my Google Scholar Page.

**J Schroeder**, J Suh, C Wilks, M Czerwinski, SA Munson, J Fogarty, T Althoff. <u>Data-Driven Implications for Translating Evidence-Based Psychotherapies into Technology-Delivered Interventions</u>. *PervasiveHealth* 2020.

**J Schroeder**, R Karkar, N Murinova, J Fogarty, SA Munson. <u>Examining Opportunities for Goal-Directed Self-Tracking to Support Chronic Condition Management</u>. *UbiComp* 2020.

CF Chung, Q Wang, **J Schroeder**, A Cole, J Zia, J Fogarty, SA Munson. Identifying and Planning for Individualized Change: Patient-Provider Collaboration Using Lightweight Food Diaries in Healthy Eating and Irritable Bowel Syndrome. *UbiComp* 2019.

**J Schroeder**, R Karkar, J Fogarty, JA Kientz, SA Munson, M Kay. <u>A Patient-Centered Proposal for Bayesian Analysis of Self-Experiments for Health</u>. *JHIR 2018*.

**J Schroeder,** CF Chung, DA Epstein, R Karkar, A Parsons, N Murinova, J Fogarty, SA Munson. Examining Self-Tracking by People with Migraine: Goals, Needs, and Opportunities in a Chronic Health Condition. *DIS* 2018. Best Paper Honorable Mention.

**J Schroeder**, C Wilks, K Rowan, A Toledo, A Paradiso, M Czerwinski, G Mark, MM Linehan. <u>Pocket Skills:</u> A Conversational Mobile Web App To Support Dialectical Behavioral Therapy. *CHI 2018*.

R Karkar, **J Schroeder**, D Epstein, L Pina, J Scofield, J Fogarty, JA Kientz, SA Munson, R Vilardaga, J Zia. TummyTrials: A Feasibility Study of Using Self-Experimentation to Detect Individualized Food Triggers. *CHI 2017*. Best Paper Honorable Mention.

CF Chung, E Agapie, **J Schroeder**, S Mishra, J Fogarty, S Munson. When Personal Tracking Becomes Social: Examining the Use of Instagram for Healthy Eating. *CHI* 2017.

D Epstein, N Lee, J Kang, E Agapie, **J Schroeder**, L Pina, J Fogarty, JA Kientz, SA Munson. <u>Examining Menstrual Tracking to Inform the Design of Personal Informatics Tools</u>. *CHI 2017*. Best Paper Awardee.

**J Schroeder**, J Hoffswell, CF Chung, J Fogarty, S Munson, J Zia. Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. *CSCW* 2017.

### **SELECT WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS**

Personalizing Health Technologies to Support Patient and Provider Goals. CSCW 2019 Workshop on Identifying Challenges and Opportunities in Human–AI Collaboration in Healthcare.